[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
let's come back to general relativity or
any questions about the contraction yes
yes yes yes yes yes good good I meant to
do that
right Utama Jimmy new Jim you know Jim
you knew Jim you knew and Jimmy knew
right okay so Jim Ian was a tensor with
took over with two covariant indices two
downstairs indices it has a version with
upstairs indices and by convention or by
definition the G mu nu with upstairs
indices think of this as a matrix think
of it as a matrix in the case of
four-dimensional space-time it's a four
by four matrix I'm not going to write
down all of its entries this matrix is G
you know and Jean you knew with upper
indices is also a matrix it's also a
matrix it's the matrix of entries with
upper indices but the matrix with upper
indices is simply defined as them as the
inverse of the matrix with lower indices
that means if you multiply them together
as matrices what's the result of
multiplying a matrix by the inverse of
itself the unit matrix the unit matrix
is the matrix 1 1 1 1 with zeros
everywhere else will bother writing the
zeros in that's statement number 1 so we
have these two matrices which are
related by the fact that their product
is the unit matrix let's just talk about
multiplying matrices for a minute if I
write matrices a matrix in the form of
let's not let's not worry for the moment
about upper and lower indices upper and
lower indices are very important when
you're doing differential geometry and
so forth but just matrices and matrix
with entries a B
and I want to multiply it by another
matrix with whose entries are or whose
indices are another name another word
another letter for a matrix q Q okay Q
we're multiplying the matrix M by the
matrix Q all right so the way that you
multiply it is just you put M a B next
day q BC and then you multiply the
entropy entries and sum over the
repeated index that gives you the matrix
product mq AC all right so what does
that mean about G mu nu and G mu nu here
if we multiply this matrix by this
matrix we should get the unit matrix all
right so let's let's use the rule for
matrix multiplication first we write
down the matrix G now let's give it I
don't want to use mu nu I'm going to use
some arbitrary indices alpha and beta
and next to it this is the matrix with
lower indices next to it we put the
other matrix that were multiplying by it
right next to it G B or beta gamma
that's the same combination or the same
logic that we have here ma b QB c GG
alpha beta G beta gamma and sum over
beta
that gives us a matrix with an alpha
entry or alpha index and a gamma index
now notice over here we didn't pay any
attention to covariant and Convery and
covariant and contravariant components
we just thought about ordinary matrix
products here we have a matrix with
covariant and
see Zorka tensor with covariant indices
multiplying a tensor with contravariant
indices and summing over beta but that's
the matrix product of these two matrices
what is the matrix product the matrix
product is the matrix with ones along
the diagonal
that's the chronica Delta all right now
it's from from the notation and
consistency of notation I could write
that this is Delta Alpha Gamma yeah yeah
we don't really want to put that gamma
upstairs Downstairs
why not well just a consistency of
tensor notation covariant and
contravariant sort of suggests so pretty
much insist that we put the gamma
upstairs but it is just the kronecker
delta 0 if alpha does not equal gamma 1
if alpha equals gamma so intentional
notation the Kronecker Delta is always a
thing with an upstairs index and a
downstairs index so from now on whenever
I use the Kronecker Delta don't be
surprised to see it with one upstairs
and one downstairs index that's number
one now number two let's talk about
raising and lowering the a tensor index
supposing I have a tensor with upstairs
indices and I want to lower one of the
indices so let's take some general
tensor T beta gamma and I want to lower
the beta index what I do is I multiply
it by G alpha beta and sum over beta
that lowers the index and it gives me
the tensor T alpha gamma
okay let's compare that with what's
going on here here I have the matrix G
with upper indices so we can it's the
replacement if you like for T beta gamma
in this formula next to it I have the
metric G alpha beta which is exactly
what I have over here when I combine
these two together what does it give me
according to this formula according to
this formula
it gives me t with one lower and one
upper index but T is just G so it gives
me the metric tensor with one out with
one lower index and one upper index so
the metric tensor with one lower index
and one upper index is always just Delta
alpha gamma it doesn't depend on
position
it's just Delta alpha gamma it's one of
the few tensors that will meet in
geometry which doesn't depend on one of
the few sets of components which is just
a numerical set of components which does
not depend on position G over here may
depend on position G over here may
depend on position but because what's
over here is always the inverse of this
Delta Alpha Gamma does not depend on
position it's always just this matrix so
that's the answer to the question what
is the tensor the the metric tensor with
one lower index and one upper index and
the answer is that it's the chronica
delta set again here no from this
combination what is this combination
alright in this combination here this g
is playing the role of this T right okay
so let's let's call it
T
I don't want to call it a I'm gonna call
it G okay but all I'm doing is
substituting wherever I see G here I'm
sorry wherever I see T over here I'm
substituting G over here okay the rule
is that if you take tea with two upper
index and multiply it by G you get tea
with one upper index and one lower index
well what is T tea is G in this formula
[Music]
Alpha Gamma yeah yeah yeah equals yeah
oh I'm sorry okay yeah this this yes
it's just this whole left-hand side is
equal to this by definition that's a
that's essentially a definition two
definitions going on one is the
definition of how you raise and lower
indices and the other is the definition
of G with upper indices that it's the
inverse of the G with lowering these
indices right so whenever you find
yourself wanting to use G with one index
upper and one index lower it's the it's
the chronica Delta now that that tells
us something yeah supposing you want to
contract an upper index and a lower
index supposing you have some tensor T
alpha beta and you want to form a scalar
out of it to form a scalar out of it you
can multiply it by the metric or are you
first of all you can just identify beta
with alpha and contract the beta with
alpha or you can just think of it as
multiplying it by G beta Delta beta
alpha which is just G in some other
notation let's write several different
formulas certain formulas all right
first of all there's T alpha beta which
if I want to make a scale
out of it I multiply it by G alpha beta
and sum of alpha and beta that makes a
scaler alright that's one way to make a
scalar another way which is equal and
you can prove this I leave it to you to
prove is to take T with lower components
and multiply it by G we raised
components same thing that you need to
work out okay to see that that's true
but you can also take it to be T with
one upper index one lower index
multiplied by G with one lower index and
one upper index they're all three equal
to each other and in this form this is
just a chronica delta x t alpha beta
now the chronica Delta is either 0 or 1
depending on whether alpha equals beta
so it's really just an instruction to
add T 1 1 plus T 2 2 plus T 3 3 plus T 4
4 and so it's exactly the same as T
alpha alpha T 1 1 plus T 2 2 plus T 3 3
and so forth I just do this too because
there was a hole that I left out of the
discussion what the metric tensor is
with one upper and one lower index
well you have to keep track in general
you should think whenever you write a
tensor think of ordering the indices
alpha beta gamma delta sigma now unless
the tensor happens to have certain
symmetries
it may have symmetries which tell you
that it doesn't change if you
interchange the indices but let's
suppose it doesn't then then you have to
keep track of the order of these indices
and if you decide to raise the beta
index put it over here okay right so
what I said is if it's a symmetric
tensor then it doesn't matter just put
it directly above yeah in other words
right may I look at directly above in
other words think mentally of putting
some partitions in and you can slide the
indices up and down with the metric
tensor
[Music]
the original question of what's the
relation between the contravariant and
covariant components of vectors and as I
told you they are connected with
expanding the vector in terms of basis
vectors or projecting the vector onto
basis vectors the same is true of them
of tensors but if you like it's just a
way of forming tensors out of tensors
forming tensors with upper indices out
of thought enters with lower indices and
you give them the same name if they're
related by by this operation they have
the same information in them geometry is
the connection between expanding things
and basis vectors and projecting onto
basis vectors so I'll I'm really gonna
leave that for you to go and look up and
find some good good discussion of
covariant and contravariant indices in
the geometric meaning there's lots of
places to look it up yeah
G has to be invertible yes right alright
if ya in ordinary geometry which means
geometry of spatial surfaces and so
forth where time is not different than
space and you don't have not Minkowski
geometry then all lengths are always
positive obviously not so in relativity
where there are space like time like and
light like directions but an ordinary
geometry all distances are always
positive so that means if you take a DX
let's for space let's just use M and n
instead of MU and nu mu and nu will be
reserved for space-time the X M DX n G
MN m n of X this must always be greater
than zero strictly greater than zero as
long as the X's are not in the X's could
be small they don't have to be
infinitesimal just small think of them
as just small little components of
vectors every vector has a positive
squared length square root of any power
the vector is always positive and so
this has to be greater than zero now if
you have a matrix which when you
multiply it on the left
tons of vector entire on the right times
the same vector and it must be positive
then there's something you can say about
that matrix did anybody know what it is
it's positive definite and that has and
that means exactly what
positive-definite i ghen values so it
means that the eigenvalues of GM in are
positive that's about all that's about
the only thing that that is required and
of course if all the eigenvalues are
positive well then the only eigenvalues
are positive yeah
any vector will have a positive squared
length so if you think of this is the
squared length now in relativity let's
go back to special relativity and
special relativity the tau squared is
equal to DT squared minus the x squared
minus dy squared minus DZ squared or
whatever and special relativity for
example now if I want to put in the
speed of light I can put in the speed of
light in to one of two ways I can either
multiply this one by the square of the
speed I need to give these the same
units this has units of length squared
this has units of x squared they're not
compatible to make them have the same
units I need some speeds of light I can
either put the speed of light squared
here but in that case what is the units
of this quantity well let's just not
worry about for the moment let's just
define yeah it's just a race this side
for a minute and let's just consider
this expression what are its units
length squared all terms in it have
units of length squared that's a
perfectly fine definition nothing wrong
with it
but I just prefer it's a it's a pure
personal preference to define the proper
time so that it has units of time the
given units of time we don't want to put
a ski C squared here we want to put the
C squared in the denominator here it's
just the same quantity except divided by
C squared and I call that D tau squared
now obviously I've put back the speed of
light and so later on when we throw away
the speed of light we'll just call this
one but what's the question anyway yeah
yeah yeah okay all right
right so the speed of light is not the
issue here but quite obviously there are
directions in which the tau squared is
positive there are for example the
directions in which all the space
components are zero and there's only a
time component a time like vector there
are directions in which D tau squared is
negative or pure space like vector so
the tau squared despite the notation as
the square of something is not really
positive definite space like vectors
have negative D tau squared time like
vectors have positive tau squared what
about light like vectors light like
vectors are vectors which have the
property that the tau equals DX for
example divided by C or equivalently the
x equals C D tau and then sorry C DT
those are vectors and then nonzero the
components are nonzero the X and DT but
they correspond to like like directions
and for them the proper time is just
plain zero so there are clearly
directions in which this is not greater
than zero these directions are which is
zero and directions which is negative
and directions in which is positive
right looking at this matron
the metric tensor the metric tensor as a
matrix would have a one and a minus one
over C squared let's get rid of the C
squared now now that I've put the C
squared and let's take it back out minus
one minus one minus
okay how many positive eigenvalues does
it have one how many negative
eigenvalues three the three negative
eigenvalues correspond to the idea that
there are three space directions and the
one positive eigenvalue corresponds to
the idea that there's one time like
direction the metric and relativity
general and special must have a feature
that there are three times three space
like directions which means three
negative eigenvalues and one positive
now now I should tell you that if you
compare with much in the literature
depending on how old the literature is
depending on the tastes of the author
and depending on how quirky the author
is one sometimes defines instead of the
the proper time one defines a proper
spatial interval and one defines it this
way the s squared s for space and
defines it as the x squared plus dy
squared plus DZ squared minus C squared
DT squared that's clearly the same thing
except for a factor of C C squared and a
negative sign they are the same thing
and so so far there's no difference
between what I would write down with
everybody else to write down the tau
squared is a pape thing the S squared is
a bottom thing but sometimes the metric
is read off this expression in which
case the metric would be 1 1 1 minus 1
now it's not that the met is not that
the physics is different it's just the
definition of what you mean by squared
length is different
in one case you think of squared length
as being a time like object proper time
in the other case you think of it as
being a space like object
and so it depending on notation there
are many many many physicists who like
the metric to be 1 1 1 minus 1 I use
minus 1 1 1 1 why I don't know I guess
it's because I am a maverick and I warn
you that I almost everybody uses the
other notation
I think Einstein used the same as I
don't remember sorry
yeah you might put the minus 1 up here
and one down and one down here doesn't
matter right so so in one set of
conventions you would say that the
eigenvalues are three positives for the
three directions of space and one
negative in the other set of conventions
you would say one positive for time and
three negative for space the main thing
is to be consistent you can use either
whichever you like but be consistent
essentially all the formulas are the
same no matter which way you do it you
just have to remember in the end what
you're doing it'll always come back to
the special relativity description which
one you're doing are you talking about
proper time or are you talking about
proper distance proper space like this
thinness okay so with that warning again
I can't remember what the question was
the properties of the metric yes can be
anything at all within reason
smooth differentiable or and not always
sometimes it's allowed to have certain
singularities but mostly you want it to
be smooth differentiable like any other
field
invertible symmetric symmetric lovely
Romani and simply means it's smooth
means that it's continuous and may be
differentiable but even that's not
necessary
just that it's a smooth the smooth
metric let's write down the conditions
let's write them down help me out
because they don't remember smooth which
means continuous and differentiable and
you can differentiate it as many times
as is necessary in a calculation so just
assume it's smooth enough to
differentiate as many times as you need
to smooth ok what was it what was next
invertible now that well let's let's
let's put in before invertible let's put
symmetric
let's put symmetric now where did the
symmetric come from incidentally
remember it's definition it's D tau
squared equals G mu nu DX mu DX nu what
would happen if there was an
anti-symmetric piece to jamia no any
matrix can be written as a sum of
symmetric and anti-symmetric the
anti-symmetric means that when you
interchange the indices it changes sign
what would happen if G mu nu was
anti-symmetric you would get zero from
this you will get zero from this because
the coefficient for example of the x 1
DX 2 would be opposite to the
coefficient of DX 2 DX 1 but they're the
same thing the product the x1 and the x2
so if it was anti-symmetric you wouldn't
get anything any matrix can be written
as a sum of symmetric and anti-symmetric
only the symmetric part of G mu nu will
contribute so you might as well
say the gym you knew is symmetric right
now any matrix any terms that you would
put in or anti-symmetric wouldn't
wouldn't affect anything so there would
be sort of spurious no physics to them
nothing could determine them since
they're arbitrary so yes it's it is a
yes it is a it is a question of
convenience yes yes it is a question of
convenience
absolutely but once it's symmetric then
you can say that it has eigenvalues and
how many eigenvalues does it have in
general it will have a full set of
eigenvalues equal to the dimensionality
of the space so there will be for
example in four-dimensional space-time
for eigenvalues so it will have by
virtue of it being symmetric they will
have a set of eigenvalues
what is the condition that the matrix be
invertible nonzero determinant but that
simply means no zero eigenvalues all
right because the determinant is just a
product of the eigenvalues so invertible
simply precludes zero eigen values eigen
values which are zero that's all this
means once it's symmetric it's
invertible but then on top of that it
should have depending on the application
if we're talking about ordinary space
versus space time in ordinary space it
should have all positive eigenvalues and
of course we would be talking about the
s square then not the tau squared in
ordinary space all positive eigenvalues
and we would say the language that
mathematicians use
as they would say the signature of the
space of the space would be plus plus
plus plus plus plus is the signature of
the space and it's simply telling you
how many positive and negative
eigenvalues if I use this notation here
where I study the proper time I would
say that the that that the signature of
the metric was minus plus plus plus one
minus and three pluses so for the
purposes of general relativity or
relativity in general the signature of
the metric is plus minus minus minus in
other words this means three negative
eigenvalues in one positive eigenvalue
those are the conditions for a metric to
be an allowable metric symmetric
guarantees
good yes I'm not positive right
absolutely
okay so that's that's the conditions on
metric now you might there are important
dynamical conditions for example the
gravitational field is the metric it's
the thing which satisfies equations of
motion how do I know that my equations
of motion won't suddenly at some point
in time change the signature of the a
for example how do i know that some g
m-- you know let's say 1 minus 1 1 minus
1 minus 1 minus 1 won't evolve in time
and eventually become 1 1 minus 1 minus
1 that better not happen this is this is
not an allowable metric to describe a
sensible space-time to space directions
in 1/2 time directions bad news that's
not a good thing why doesn't that happen
what is the dynamics what's what is it
in the equations of the theory and the
evolutionary equations of the theory
which tells things how to change from
moment to moment which precludes this
from happening well I can tell you one
thing what's the determinant of a metric
with 1 minus 1 minus 1 minus 1 these are
the eigenvalues i'm specifying the
eigenvalues what's the determinant of
the metric here minus 1 what's the
determinant of the metric here plus 1
sum where's the metric will have had to
go through having determinant zero so if
there's something in the dynamics that
forbids determinant going to 0 some sort
of effect in the energy or somehow in
the in the dynamics which pushes you
away from determinant 0 some dynamics
which is a which repels the metric away
from determinant 0
then it can't change signature and of
course in general relativity there is
such an effect passing through zero
would cost infinite amounts of energy
and and so it doesn't happen or if it
does happen it's extremely pathological
I don't know any PK any case where it
happens ok so that's those are good
questions
now we come to Feinstein's equations and
so forth but before we do
[Music]
no change there's no way that you can go
from a positive determinant to a
negative determinant smoothly
remember the metric is smooth so
supposing over here supposing in this
point over here in space-time the
determinant of the metric incidentally
the determinant of the metric is usually
just called G like that it's the product
of the eigenvalues all right
supposing the determinant of the metric
over here was - in other words supposing
the signature was 1 minus 1 minus 1
minus 1 and then it wants to make a
transition in some other place over here
it's gonna have the opposite metric of
the opposite determinant here it's
positive or negative sorry negative here
it's positive well here's some curves
smooth curve between them someplace if
the metric is smooth it's going to have
to go to 0 and those are the kind of
places where where the equations push
you away from those places and that's
generally true that a change it's
generally true that the equations push
you away from places where the signature
of the metric might change on you so
that's a good thing space-time cannot
change into space it space-time cannot
suddenly become 4 dimensions of space
that would be very awkward nor can it
suddenly become 2 dimensions of time in
two dimensions of space there are there
are dynamics which prevent that from
happening okay
let's let's come to seeing what we can
learn about as much as possible that we
can learn about the equations of motion
the field equations of general
relativity we're not going to go through
the whole business the whole business is
a bit tedious we may or may not get to
that tonight but no now something
happens at the singularity of a black
hole expect everything to get nasty and
all bets are off when you come to places
like singularities of black holes it's
not that the metric changes signature
from from space the time or something
like that just the smoothness breaks
down and components of the metric well
curvatures become infinite bad things
happen but those are the exceptional
cases which are of course the subject of
black holes and singularity theorems and
things of that nature
okay and it's not that they were
irrelevant they're quite relevant but
for the moment let's say temporarily
let's just ignore or not ignore but
let's pretend that there are no
singularities
alright let's talk about the begin with
the what we want to compare is Newton
we've done this in various situations
with some ideas from Einstein and try to
put together or try to guess the
equations the tensor equations that
replace the Newtonian equations to do so
if we're going to think about the
Newtonian equations the Newtonian
equations are the Einstein equations in
certain limits there are certain limits
where certain things are big and other
things are small let's see if we can
figure out what things are likely to be
big and what things are likely to be
small and then systematically think of
nonrelativistic limit as the limit in
which small things are really much
smaller than big things and of course
what we're talking about mainly being
small is velocities velocities on the
one hand and also the strength of
gravitational fields the strength of
gravitational fields should not be too
big that entails saying either that no
object in your theory is so compact and
so compressed that that the acceleration
due to gravity becomes enormous or it
can just mean stay away from such
objects stay far away from such objects
which of course are black holes but
slowly moving things with relatively
weak gravitational fields are the
subject of Newton right well first of
all the first thing to say is that the
metric under such circumstances in a
frame of reference where everything is
moving slowly is close to the ordinary
nonrelativistic metric that means that
apart from small quantities G naught
naught is 1 I'm gonna write 1 plus small
and we're gonna keep track of small
things all right but we're gonna keep
track of them to the leading water
basically all right it also means that
what about g11 well that's equal to
minus one plus small things what about G
2 - same thing what about G not one well
that's something that does not appear in
ordinary special relativity and so if
we're when I say I should say when I say
that that there are two limits both of
which we should keep track of one of
them is things moving very very slowly
in which case our Newton a week Fields
and slowly then Newton is the right
physics
what about week fields but you move fast
special relativity all right so we want
to we want to deal with both of those
but in special relativity G naught 1
what is G naught 1 at 0 that's not there
in special relativity where a special
relativity here's special relativity and
there were no terms multiplying DT by DX
now this is equal to zero plus small
things we can write this we can
generalize this GM n I'm not gonna write
the clinic a delta I'm just going to
write that g11 equals G - 2 equals G 3 3
equals and so forth
and g12 equals blah blah blah blah blah
equals zero now I don't literally mean
this that they're literally equal to
zero I mean they're equal to zero plus
small plus small we will keep track of
small things but the first approximation
is just special relativity now next
let's concentrate on energy and momentum
we're going to be dealing with the
energy momentum tensor and the energy
momentum tensor is essentially the
right-hand side of Einstein's equations
it's the sources of a gravitational
field energy of course is the same as
mass through the equals mc-squared
relationship mass is the source of
gravitational field and so energy is the
source of gravitational field but since
we're forced to write tensor equations
in some frame of reference we may have
an energy in some other frame of
reference that same energy turns into
energy and the momentum in a frame of
reference where there's some energy if
we move past that energy that means
there's some mass there if we move past
that energy then of course we see some
momentum so momentum and energy go
together and if we're going to be
writing tensor equations we should
expect on the right-hand side of those
equations some of the equations will
have momentum in them as sources of the
gravitational field in other words the
energy momentum tensor is the important
thing but which components of the energy
momentum tensor are likely to be big and
small in the slow weak field limit so
let's begin with the ordinary energy of
a particle what's the energy of a
particle of mass m and free space MV
squared over 2 good
one-half MV squared over 2 no just 1/2
MV square and remember V is small
what's the momentum
and me this is energy this is momentum
momentum this is a P and V alright V is
small remember that V is small so which
one of these is bigger MV right
yeah it's true MV is bigger than MV
squared but we forgot a term here MC
squared
every object of mass M has an energy MC
C is bigger than anything in sight M
times let's write this as M times C
times C well MC is certainly bigger than
MV because C is big 3 times 10 to the
8th meters per second per second 3 times
10 to the 8 meters per second and C is
doubly big here so this is typically
much bigger than MV the biggest thing
around in terms of energy and momentum
for a massive object you know for star
or for a for a thing which gravitates
the big term in the energy momentum
tensor is the energy density all of the
other terms are much smaller because
they don't have the MC squared energy
how can you compare thing to different
units oh you mean in compared with
momentum yeah well okay we can we can we
can work out what we can do is work in
units where the speed of light is warm
okay then then they will have the same
units if we work in units with it yeah
and one of them ISM that means
velocities have units of no units right
so the the right statement is the right
statement is in a dimensionless sense
namely the sense in which we choose the
speed of light to be equal to one
typically momenta are much much smaller
than than than energies energies have
this big whopping MC squared term and
momenta we the other way to say it we
can either say it MC squared is big
because C is big and this doesn't have
any C in it the other way to say it is
that in units in which C is equal to one
we have an energy which is M but then we
have a momentum which is terribly small
because the velocity is small
okay comes to the same thing
sometimes it's fun to keep track of the
speeds of light just to see what's big
and what's small okay meaning of this is
that the first approximation for a
gravitating object for the source of a
gravitational field if that object is at
rest or not moving well at rest means
moving slowly compared to the speed of
light then the energy momentum tensor
really only has one significant
component T naught naught the energy
density the momentum that the energy
flux the objects not moving very fast
the energy flux will be small the
momentum density will be small the flux
of momentum will be small everything is
small except T naught naught
and what does T naught naught T naught
naught is the energy density now I keep
every mob will keep reminding you energy
density and mass density are the same
thing if I choose the speed of light
equal to one so to the first
approximation the big chunk and the
energy momentum tensor is just the mass
density and everything else being zero
plus small okay so that's something we
should keep in mind when we're trying to
compare when we're trying to compare
with known physics so to speak I mean
what was Einstein's situation he had
these geometric ideas he thought gravity
had to do with the metric of space-time
but he needed some equations the first
thing to do was to make sure that in the
limit when Newton ought to apply or in
the limit where special relativity auto
apply that they do apply so that was the
first test if you like or the first
criteria a principle of correspondence
with known physics
okay that's metric basically special
relativity if we keep track of the
speeds of light then actually the only
the only big component of the metric is
the time time component the space-time
the space space components are smaller
by a factor of one over C squared if we
keep track of the speed of light okay if
we keep track of C in the equations and
it's useful sometimes to keep track of
the speed of light okay what else do we
know we know from Newton or generalized
NUI Newton plus Gauss plus
Plus whoever else was involved we have a
field equation that the gravitational
potential satisfies del squared Phi is
equal to 4 pi G Rho this is a disguised
form of the inverse square law and we
also found out by looking at the motion
of geodesics slowly moving particles
satisfy the usual acceleration being
acceleration is equal to minus the
derivative of the usual equation
acceleration is equal to minus a
gradient of Phi or minus the earth
component of the M component of the
acceleration is equal to the derivative
with respect to M of v minus a plus - I
think that's F equals MA except dividing
by M acceleration is the gradient of a
potential
okay so we have that and if we compare
that with the equations of a geodesic
that tells us the relationship between
the gravitational potential and a
certain component of the metric remember
we work that out for slowly moving
geodesics we found that what was it
anybody remember the formula or in
Traktor I had things written down but
unless should I write yeah I think they
are right what we found out well was
that the gravitational potential was
like 1/2 of G naught naught now that's
not right that's not correct that's not
correct what what actually did we find
out
see plus a constant what we really found
out is that the derivatives of Phi were
related to the derivative of G where did
the derivatives of G come from they came
from the Christoffel symbols only in the
equation of motion F equals MA
only derivatives of Phi appear and the
Christoffel symbols only only
derivatives of G appear so it was really
that the derivative of Phi in any
direction is the derivative of G naught
north but another way to write that is
the Phi is equal to G naught naught plus
some constant which doesn't vary in
position now again I emphasize there's a
G naught naught is equal to Phi 2 Phi
what was it - all right this design
drives me crazy I believe I do not want
to use C thank you let's call it C OMS T
constant of course the speed of light is
also a constant but I think that I don't
think it'd be unclear
okay the first equation of this Court
says the gradient of the potential
I'm sorry del squared of potential at a
point in space is equal to the density
of mass at that point in space so if
there's no mass the potential is
interchangeable be careful be careful
that that is a good question what is
what is this thing here it's the second
derivative with respect to X plus the
second derivative with respect to Y plus
the second derivative with respect to Z
all right well it says what it says is
that some are positive and some are
negative it doesn't say it doesn't say
that each one of these is zero first of
all even if it said that that each one
was zero wouldn't say was constant it
would still allow a first derivative but
that would be rather limited just having
first derivatives what it says is that
the combination of these second
derivatives have to add up to zero
that's quite a different thing than
saying it is that they are individually
zero so now the gravitational potential
does vary from place to place for
example if you take the gravitational
potential one over R one over distance
from the origin then except at the
origin itself if you work this out you
will find out that del squared of 1 over
R is equal to zero so that is a good
question and it has a good answer the
answer being that it does not say that
the individual derivatives are zero but
just a combination so at any point in
space where there is no matter this
combination is up to zero
but there are plenty of functions with
that property let's write down some
functions with that let me just write
down one function with that property
take x squared plus y squared minus 2z
squared okay what's the second
derivative that would call us fire
what's the second derivative of this
with respect to X
- how about with respect to why how
about with respect to Z minus 4 so 2
plus 2 plus minus 4 is equal to 0 ok so
this is a question this is a function
functions with this property of called
harmonic functions there's lots of them
there's no lack of harmonic functions
but they're still not as many as there
are of all functions so there are
restrictions ok now what is this object
on the on the right hand side we clearly
have something involving T naught naught
all right the gravitation of the sorry
the the mass density on the left hand
side we have something involving two
derivatives of what is in essence G
naught naught components of the metric
we don't have to worry about this
constant the first derivative gets rid
of the constant and the second
derivative gives us some second
derivative of G naught naught so what's
on the left hand side involves second
derivatives of G naught naught there are
not a lot of tensors that are made up
out of second derivatives of G naught
naught there are relatively few of them
basically only two geometric tensors
that are made up out of gene or not what
we actually want to have on the right
hand side is team you know in the
generalized equation I'm not saying that
this is equal to this I'm saying the
more general equation that we would like
to be the tensor analog of this will
have the energy momentum tensor on the
right hand side maybe maybe some 4 PI G
maybe some constant let's call it K for
constant and on the left hand side we
need some tensor with two indices which
is made up out of the second derivatives
of the the metric second derivatives of
the metric that should ring a bell
sounds like the
which a tensor it can't be the Riemann
tensor because that has four indices it
can be the Ricci tensor the first thing
that Einstein tried was just mu nu equal
that okay
he ran into grief the reason that I ran
into grief had to do with energy
momentum conservation let's write down
what in ordinary non-relative an
ordinary I suppose special relativity
the conservation of energy momentum let
me just remind you go slow the
conservation of charge the conservation
of charge was expressed in terms of a
current and the current had an index mu
the time component was density the space
component was the flow of charge and
anybody remember what the equation is
for for continuity equation well just
derivative ordinary derivative I can
also be expressed in terms of a
covariant derivative but ordinary you
know an ordinary flat special relativity
it's D mu J mu is equal to zero also in
special relativity there's a
conservation of energy and momentum each
component of the energy and the momentum
are conserved and that became the
equation D mu of T mu nu is equal to
zero nu here tells you whether you're
talking about energy and momentum mu
tells you whether you're talking about
the density or the flow and so for each
new this is a continuity equation the
correct continuity equation then we'll
come to this I'll explain difference in
a little while but the correct
continuity equation is that the in this
form it doesn't really make sense why
not because it's not a covariant
derivative incidentally
we're gonna have to come back to why
this one does make sense but let's let's
just focus on the energy momentum tensor
the right equation is this one but the
covariant thats a nice tensor equation
if it's true in one frame its true in
every frame covariant derivative of T mu
nu is equal to zero for the charge
density the covariant derivative and the
ordinary derivative can be taken to be
the same for technical reasons that I
may or may not ever get to but let's
concentrate on the energy momentum
tensor it should satisfy Del mu T mu nu
equals zero that should be a property of
the energy momentum tensor without it
there would be no conservation of energy
we must have in special relativity and
in general relativity we also expect us
expect some kind of local flow of energy
and momentum we expect it to be
conserved we don't expect energy to
disappear and reappear in distant places
and so that says that a certain
covariant derivative of T mu nu is equal
to zero we can try that out over here on
the left hand on the right hand side we
can take del mu of T mu nu times Kappa
times K times this constant K and
according to this equation it would say
that del mu of our mu nu is equal to
zero in other words conservation of
energy momentum would demand that this
property be true of the ramond of the
Ricci tensor well it turns out that that
property of the Ricci tensor is almost
never true basically it would require
it's just a property of the Ricci tensor
it's it's never true and it's it's a
false theorem or a false identity where
Einstein wanted was for the left hand
side to be an identity
automatic so that energy-momentum tensor
the sorry so that energy momentum
conservation would be a consequence of
his equations he wanted to follow the
pattern of Maxwell's equations Maxwell's
equations have the property that their
connections between the electric and
magnetic fields on one side something
involving a and B on one side whatever
it is and on the other side what's on
the other side the charge density and
the current well Maxwell's equations
have the property that whatever is on
the left-hand side automatically as an
identity in other words for every way
for every electric and magnetic field
that you can write down that you can
build up out of the out of the out of
the vector potential that the derivative
is automatically zero and so what you
can say about Maxwell's equations is
that charge conservation follows from
the form of Maxwell's equations it's not
something you have to add the Maxwell's
equations it follows from Maxwell's
equations Einstein wanted the same
pattern he wanted energy and momentum
conservation to be an automatic Konica
consequence of his field equations and
for that he would have had to have that
dumb you arm you knew the covariant
gradient of arm you know covariant
divergence of arm you knew should be
zero for every arm you know but just
isn't true you take a general
differential geometry and you calculate
the this let's call this the the
covariant grade covariant divergence of
arm you know it's not equal to zero when
he calculated it how do you how do you
calculate it you put in forearm you knew
its expression in terms of the
Christoffel symbols and then actually I
think that's all you need I don't think
you even really need to write the
Christoffel symbols and
of the metric but to use the expression
for arm you knew in terms of the
Christoffel symbols you know what
covariant derivative means it means
ordinary derivative plus a thing with
some Christoffel symbols and you simply
work it out and what you find is let's
see if I can find it
damn it yeah
here's the identity that you find you
find that del mu nu sorry dum you of our
mu nu is not equal to zero it happens to
be equal to one-half G mu nu times the
derivative with respect to mu of the
scalar curvature everybody remember what
the scalar curvature is there was the
Riemann curvature the Ricci curvature
which you got by contracting two indices
and left over two indices and the
curvature scalar you got by contracting
the remaining indices of the reach each
of the Ricci tensor that's what he found
now I don't know for how long that
puzzled him I don't know how long it
took him to put two and two together but
after a while he realized the following
facts first of all the Riemann curve it
the the curvature scalar here is a
scalar
what's the covariant derivative of a
scalar no no no that's zero it's just
the ordinary derivative the partial
derivative yeah the ordinary partial
derivative so this could be replaced by
covariant derivative now covariant
derivatives are a little bit strange but
they satisfy the usual rules that the
covariant derivative of a product could
be product of any to any tensors I'm not
even going to write indices for them any
two tensors a and B satisfy the usual
rule
a times the covariant derivative or b
plus plus the covariant derivative of a
times b covariant derivatives do have
that property at least they have that
property so now we look at this over
here
number one and we say wait a minute
remember the fact that the covariant
derivative of the metric tensor is zero
the covariant derivative of the metric
tensor with upper or lower it doesn't
matter or doesn't matter where you put
the indices the covariant derivative of
the metric tensor is zero so you can
also write this as one-half the
covariant derivative of G mu nu times R
why is that
well this contains G mu nu times the
covariant derivative R but it also
contains R times the covariant
derivative of G mu nu the last term
being zero so you discovered them you
knew of arm you know is equal to
one-half del mu nu of G mu nu R now I
don't know if this was known before
Einstein or not I don't know that
anybody ever had any particular reason
to calculate the covariant derivative of
arm you know the covariant divergence
like that and how many weeks months days
hours or seconds it took for n Stein to
say hey wait a minute I can now take
this over to the left hand side and
write that this is equal to Del mu nu
del mu times R mu nu minus 1/2 G mu nu R
is equal to zero that was the big
breakthrough that was the big
breakthrough realizing that there was in
fact is and was in fact a certain tensor
that can be made up out of the Ricci
tensor and the Ricci scalar times G mu
nu which has automatically
automatically for any metric doesn't
matter what the metric is for any metric
whatever the del mu of this tensor here
is automatically zero it's an identity
if you plug in for R mu nu its
expression in terms of the Christoffel
symbols you'll find this to be true okay
and again I emphasize you don't need to
put in any special form for the metric
all the important thing is that it be
differentiable enough to be able to do
all the derivatives other than that it
will always be equal to zero
so that first of all
Einstein gave us a name very modestly he
called the Einstein tensor I don't know
who quality it wasn't Einstein he could
have called the mu nu but he didn't he
called it Jimmy oh no no sorry yeah del
mu G mu nu equals zero g mu nu is just
the Ricci tensor minus 1/2 G mu nu times
the curvature scalar once he realized
this he knew what he had to do next what
he had to do next was replace this
inconsistent equation was inconsistent
at least it was inconsistent with energy
momentum conservation
[Music]
still in flunkies yeah yeah six four
equations yes four equations yes for
continuity equations these are not the
field equations of Einstein the field
equations are the other ones over here
these are the continuity equations for
energy momentum there's a continuity
equation for energy there's a continuity
equation for the X component of momentum
another one for the Y component another
one for the Z component and so forth
four distinct equations that Express the
local continuity of energy and momentum
and they are the closest thing that
there is the energy momentum
conservation in in gravity now there's a
certain point that I'm going to come to
that's a little bit subtle about why
they don't express conservation the
usual sense but we'll come to it soon
and we shouldn't expect it to but let's
let's go we'll come to it soon enough
all right so Einstein said nope let's
put G mu nu here
arm you know minus one half G mu nu oh
sorry
arm you know with upstairs in the sea
yes
we are
the energy-momentum tensor is symmetric
no now I I haven't I haven't gone into
the question of the symmetry of the
energy-momentum tensor the symmetry of
the energy-momentum tensor is required
by Lorentz invariants and I think it
would just take us outside the scope of
these lectures but what consists one can
say is that the Einstein equations
require team unit to be symmetric so
just as it requires team you know to be
conserved
it also requires it to be symmetric and
if you look at the Tenergy momentum
tensor for any kind of reasonable field
theory it's always symmetric tensor
equation a tensor or some of what
there's nothing to sum here
there's no repeated indices in those
equations leaving some of this in this
sum of what
and
sorry some of what you can't say that
some of and pina on the other side for
some of what and what
no this is 16 equations 4 times 4 16
dependent equations so there are 16
Einstein now they're not all completely
independent there are relationships
among them but at first sight
and without being too subtle these are
the 16 independent Einstein equations
just like Maxwell's equations how many
Maxwell's equations are there let's see
Delta L 1 to the 8th Maxwell equations
there are 69 Stine equations right for
the various components of the
gravitational field
we captured
in four dimensions of
doesn't have to be 0bg - that's correct
so again in Texas within this curvature
if the Ricci tensor is zero that's right
so that means that we get stress energy
energy-momentum tensor but you don't
have a flat space let's go through the
cases first possibility is the energy
let's take the case where the energy
momentum tensor is zero okay energy
momentum no energy momentum whatever
then the right hand side is zero let's
see what we can say that says that arm
you know minus one half G mu nu R is
equal to zero so far it's not obvious
that it says that our mu nu is zero but
it does or which i think is what you
were getting at
[Music]
yes here's your what you're saying is
correct but let me just say it in its
general form take this equation here and
contract it with G mu nu lower index
okay
what is the contraction of G mu nu with
R mu nu are just to the scalar R so what
this is then is its R minus 1/2 and what
is the contraction of G mu nu Oh G mu nu
whoa not quite we're summing over both
indices okay good let's let's do it
let's work it out okay I want G mu nu
times G mu nu right so let's back off
for a moment and do something a little
simpler let's take G alpha nu g nu mu
what is that
that's the chronica Delta that's the
chronica Delta Delta alpha mule but now
I want to identify alpha with Miu also
because that's what I have here Jim you
know Jim you know so what happens if I
identify alpha with mu then this becomes
mu and this becomes mu also what is
Delta mu mu no no I heard one I heard -
I heard four four is of course the right
answer why because it's the sum of the
four components it's the one one
component plus the two two component
plus the three three component plus the
four four component so this number is
four and put a nice thing to remember
Delta mu mu remember it's summoned
there's four so let's see what we have
here and we now have minus one half
times four times R minus one half times
four if I remember correctly is minus
two so this is minus two times R is
equal to zero in other words minus R is
equal to 0 which means plus R is equal
to 0 r is equal to zero now this is
remember what this is this is the case
where there is no energy momentum so
first of all it says that the curvature
scalar is equal to zero if there's no
energy momentum around the curvature
scalar is equal to zero this is kind of
like del squared Phi equals zero doesn't
mean that the that that the metric is
trivial
it just says some particular thing is
zero about the metric but if R is equal
to zero let's come back now let's come
back now to the original equation before
we contracted it if R is equal to zero
then we can also say that our mu nu is
equal to zero so the right statement is
that in regions of space and time where
there is no energy and momentum the
Ricci tensor is equal to zero now what
does that say in three-dimensional space
for two dimensional space the Ricci
tensor being 0 would say the space is
flat in four-dimensional space-time the
Ricci tensor being 0 is not enough to
tell you the space time is flat there
are too many components too many
independent components what kind of
things can you imagine can be going on
let's imagine a spacetime which is
completely empty of matter
meaning mass meaning right hand side a
spacetime which is everywhere is
completely empty does that mean that
it's flat no it means that the Ricci
tensor is everywhere is zero
are there geometries which have Ricci
tensor equal to zero everywhere is but
aren't flat yes indeed there are anybody
have an idea what those geometries
correspond to what's that no no these
are these are geometries with a
signature plus plus plus minus I mean
the user you know good space-time well
oh yes of course
no no geometries which are not flat
Euclidean geometry is flat
are there geometries what might they
correspond to physically gravitational
waves just gravitational waves moving by
waves waves wave-like disturbances of
space-time which are not trivial for
example there are plane wave
gravitational excitations in which the
various components of the metric wobble
and wiggle but where the Ricci tensor is
everywhere zero but the Riemann tensor
is not so there are solutions
empties or we call it they're usually
called vacuum solutions they're called
vacuum solutions because they don't
contain any ordinary energy and momentum
but they do contain gravitational waves
disturbances real disturbances yes yes
okay that's a good that that that is a
very interesting point so let's come
let's come to it right now let's face it
head-on here's our equation of energy
momentum conservation the only team you
knew is equal to zero this is not the
same thing as d mu T mu nu is equal to
zero this equation is the ordinary
continuity equation and it's the
equation which expresses the idea that
if you have a region space the change of
quantity for example charge if this were
d mu J mu is equal to zero this kind of
equation here expresses the idea that if
the charge changes inside a region then
the only way it can do so is by flowing
outside this equation is different that
has an extra term in it there's a D mu
has ad mu team u nu plus another term
with some gammas and so forth what's
going on here is that this here is the
energy and momentum of everything except
for the gravitational waves
it's the right-hand source it's a term
which expresses the sources of the
gravitational field but it does not
contain the energy and the momentum in
the gravitational field that and that's
why by itself you don't have an
conservation and general relativity and
general relativity if you take only the
energy that appears on the right-hand
side of the equation it's not conserved
why because the gravitational field also
has energy and momentum it's different
than electrodynamics in electrodynamics
charge is the source of the electric and
magnetic fields the electric and
magnetic fields do not have charge they
are completely uncharged so if electric
charge is conserved it's because the
electric charge of things like electrons
and protons and neutrons is conserved
and you don't have to worry about the
electric charge of electromagnetic waves
there is none but in gravitational
theory the wave-like disturbances of the
gravitational field themselves carry
energy and momentum and therefore energy
and momentum is more complicated if some
of it comes from ordinary stuff and some
of it comes from these gravitational
waves we'll come back to this
regarding the gravitational waves that
this definitely pertain to let's see the
universe it has no master intervene it
somehow has gravitational ways and
therefore a universe that has no nothing
but gravitational waves has no team you
knew on the right hand side it does have
these wave-like disturbances the
wave-like disturbances do have energy
and momentum so effectively this cannot
be the whole energy in momentum right
Einstein understood that there's another
thing you can write down which is the
total energy and momentum but the thing
that goes on the right-hand side is not
the whole total energy momentum it's
almost as if it's analogous to the
situation which would exist if photons
are electric and magnetic fields had
charge then the charge of ordinary
charges ordinary charges ordinary I now
mean protons electrons and so forth they
would be the sources of the
electromagnetic field
but the electromagnetic field when it
was radiated off would carry off charge
if photons were charged and so the
electrons plus the protons by themselves
would not have a conserved charge in
fact you could even say more you could
even say well if the photons themselves
are charged they are sources of their
own cells when a photon is accelerated
it could bounce off a mirror it should
emit some more photons that's the way
gravity is gravity gravity is a field
which is sourced by energy momentum but
it also carries energy momentum not not
on the right-hand side of this equation
but are the pieces of energy momentum so
that when gravitons are accelerated they
will emit other gravitons so it's a more
complicated kind of store it's nonlinear
all right we're coming will little
discuss this again but let's see now
what we can learn we have a guests now
this was Einsteins guests for the
gravitational field equations the
hardest part of this little exercise is
to show this identity here
I know I know two ways to do it one of
them one of which is a one-line proof
but it requires a very sophisticated
stuff which we don't have and the other
is a mini line proof which is mechanical
straightforward I won't say mindless
that's such a right but in which you
simply plug in for the components of
their tensors their expression in terms
of the Christoffel symbols and just
check out that this relationship is true
only way I know how to do it other than
to use a fancy sophisticated argument I
started to do it and by the time I this
is when I fell asleep and I can assure
you if I were to do it on the blackboard
you would fall asleep so I won't but
it's an exercise you do yourself look it
up or just believe it okay alright so
now let's see what more we can learn
yes variational principle I'll tell you
all right if you want to know I'll tell
you what comes from there is an action
formulation of the general theory of
relativity maybe we'll get to it and
just what it says is the action is
stationary with respect to variation of
all the fields in particular stationary
with respect to the variation of G mu nu
itself and it turns out that the that
the variation of the action with respect
to G mu nu is basically the Einstein
tensor so yeah this is a fancy way to do
it but there's also a non fancy way to
do it nobody that I know of I've asked
I've asked a lot of people I mean I'm
not an expert at general relativity you
need to say you know I'm not an expert
at the technology of solving the
equations and stuff you're people who
are very very good at it they know a lot
of fancy techniques technology and ask
them do you have a simple geometric
understanding of the Einstein tensor or
even the Ricci tensor itself and
generally speaking the answer is no no
don't say anything specially simple and
especially geometric about it it just
happens to be the thing that satisfies
this identity and I have never been able
to find anybody who could reduce this
equation to a simple explanation other
than the fancy France is ever as well
was a similar question about the
fragrance and friends as everett says
basically the same thing asked about the
frame dragging terms is there a simple
geometric explanation he basically said
no well think about a little more I
think I could probably go a little
better than that for the frame dragging
but this very particular equation here
I don't know and Einstein himself just
humped it around until you found the
right thing I wish I had a simple
explanation for it I never could find
one and I never know anybody who knew
one so the worst part of it is it's not
a lot of fun to check it's rather
tedious but it's true okay so let's see
where we're going
special relativity is basically stuff on
a flat geometry frankly nice time to
figure out who you curb it that's
gravity therefore acceleration curvature
is that is a rhymin vector that doesn't
fit because there's too many components
so he shrunk it down to a reaching
vector now what I'm seeing with this
gravitational wave is that there's a
there's a difference in information
between the tensor with four components
or the two components to run adventure
effect to the tensor around this more
information of the four components of
that information that's missing is the
manifest in the form of gravitational
waves that's absolutely correct now in
three dimensions in three dimensions
let's remember for a moment what the
Riemann tensor is the Riemann tensor has
to do basically with two distinct
rotations one of the rotations or two
axes one axis is you parallel transport
around that axis the result of
parallelly transporting something around
that axis is a rotation of that
something about some other axis so when
you go around that axis with your
gyroscope the gyroscope gets rotated
about some other axis so it has to do
with two axes all right in 3-dimensional
space rotation in three-dimensional
space rotations have to do with axes in
space that's not true in four dimensions
and four dimensions they have to do with
planes in fact they always have to do
with planes it's just in three
dimensions there's a correspondence
between vectors and planes namely every
plane has the perpendicular vector
associated with it so if the Riemann
tensor has to do with pairs of rotations
pairs of rotational planes then in three
spatial dimensions it can be thought of
as having to do with pairs of axes pairs
of axes and axis is a vector right if it
has to do with pairs of axes it means
really it can be represented
something with only two indices in
general it requires four indices but in
let me tell you another reason well
another way to explain it
supposing something has a one two index
in three dimensions suppose we need
three dimensions supposing something has
a one two index then I can I can just
use a new notation in which I call it a
three index one two replaced by three
two three replaced by one pairs can be
replaced by single indices in terms of
information content so to speak so a
plane has associated with it a vector
that's the same as saying two indices
can be replaced by a third index the
other one one two gets replaced by three
two three gets replaced by you know what
I mean
okay so the answer is in three
dimensional space or even three
dimensional space-time if there was such
a thing the Ricci tensor would be a full
description and if the Ricci tensor was
zero the space is really flat okay there
is no other information and therefore in
a world of two plus one two space one
time three dimensions there are no
gravitational waves any planes place in
space where there is no material no
energy and momentum of this type space
time is flat
not just Ricci flat Ricci flap is the
statement that the Ricci tensor is zero
but just plain flat no gravitational
waves in four dimensions by the time you
get up to four dimensions then the Ricci
tensor is not a full description of the
geometry though the Ricci tensor being
zero is not enough to tell you that all
whatever the number of components of the
Riemann tensor are zero and so there's
some leftover information that leftover
information is physically in the form of
the gravitational waves
okay so that's that's the story
okay let's see how we're doing we still
have a few minutes I'm gonna try to
leave a little early tonight because I
have a very early morning flight
tomorrow there's a trick to rewrite this
equation in another form it's a kind of
neat form in which it is an equation
where R mu nu is set equal to something
else to see how it works I'm going to
show you how it works again take this
equation not this one
but the full equation and contract it
with G mu nu contract it with G mu nu
what do you get on the left-hand side
from the first term you just get the
scalar R the second term remember what
this was my minus 2r so that gives you
all together - are running out of ink -
R
and on the right-hand side you get K
times G mu nu team you know that's this
that's some scalar that's the same as
incidentally this is the same as P mu mu
contract the left or the one to contract
the two indices the right-hand side here
is some scalar that's made out of the
energy momentum tensor it's a certain
scalar that's made out of the energy
momentum tensor and the metric tensor
and it's just called T in the same way
that when you contract R mu nu with gym
you know you get just plain old r it's a
standard notation when you contract the
tensor with G mu nu the resulting scalar
carries the same letter that the tensor
started with alright so let's see so
what do we have then we have minus R
equals kapor times T where T is a thing
made up out of the energy momentum
tensor by contracting it with the with G
mu nu now we can rewrite this plugin for
R over here
that's expression over here let's see
what we get we get R mu nu minus one
half G mu nu times R but R is equal to
minus K so that'll eat up the minus sign
here there'll be a K here times the
scalar of energy and momentum T that's
not the energy density incidentally more
complicated has T naught naught that has
T 1 1 that has T 2 2 and so forth that's
equal decay Tim you know
now I can take this over to the other
side and write it that the Ricci tensor
is equal to K times T mu nu minus one
half G mu nu times T so Einstein wasn't
so far off there is a form of the
Einstein equations where it's just a
Ricci tensor is equal to something but
it's not just the energy momentum tensor
it's the energy momentum tensor minus
one half G mu nu times T it looks it
sort of looks kind of like the Einstein
tensor except made up out of the energy
momentum tensor instead of the metric
the funny kind of duality to the
equations one form the equations are a
kind of Einstein tensor made up out of G
mu nu is equal to team you know in the
other form it's a kind of Einstein ish
looking penser made up out of team you
nu is equal to R mu nu these are the two
forms of Einstein's equations and this
form happens to be convenient for some
for for sometimes solving the equations
alright let's see should we should we
quit at this point that should we go on
a little more yeah that's a class well
what's what's next week well that's
because the students are away for
Thanksgiving and but but I'm here let's
see that's you know we don't meet on
Thursday right we meet on two we meet on
Monday we meet on Monday
you know all right the next the next
step is to actually let me just tell you
what the next step is the next step is
we're gonna make the approximations of
slow things slow weak fields on both
sides of this equation here what we're
gonna find out is that the left-hand
side which is made up out of two
derivatives of the metric the most
important components of it are just del
squared Phi or del squared G naught
naught we're gonna find out that this is
good old Newton's or Laplace's del
squared Phi on the right hand side and
that on the right hand side since the
only component of team you knew which is
large and significant is T naught naught
all the other components are small what
we're gonna get on the right hand side
is going to be T naught naught or the
energy density so we're gonna find that
in the approximation where Newton is a
good approximation the time time
component of this equation two times is
basically del squared Phi is equal to
something involving the energy density
and that's going to tell us the
relationship between K or Kappa and four
PI G it is not quite that K is equal to
four PI G why not
the reason is what's small no no it's
not personal that's not the reason no
we're just trying to track down a
constant now it's this difference
between Phi and G note not the one-half
what we're gonna find out as KT as 8 pi
G instead of 4 PI G it's just as 1/2 in
the relationship between the Newtonian
potential and the metric so we'll do
that next time we'll work through that
we'll do the approximation on R naught
naught we'll see that it's basically del
squared Phi and on the right hand side
here we'll find that the right-hand side
is basically the energy
and that'll help us identify the
relationship between Newton's constant
in Kappa but basically Kappa is Newton's
constant x times an eighth cosmological
constant goes depending on which side of
the equation we put it we can put it on
either side of the equation
no we haven't addressed it yet we could
do that very fast but we won't do it
we'll do it next time
but it's another term in here yeah we
could do that remind me remind me next
time to do that it's it's really a
one-line thing
[Music]
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu